<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A touch-stone for physick directing by evident marks and characters to such medicines as without purgers, vomiters, bleedings, issues, minerals, or any other disturbers of nature may be securely trusted for cure in all extreamities and be easily distinguished from such as are hazardous or dangerous : exemplyfied by various instances of remarkable cures performed solely by such medicines.</title>
            <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9839</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12643357</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12643357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65062</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67485)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65062)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 338:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A touch-stone for physick directing by evident marks and characters to such medicines as without purgers, vomiters, bleedings, issues, minerals, or any other disturbers of nature may be securely trusted for cure in all extreamities and be easily distinguished from such as are hazardous or dangerous : exemplyfied by various instances of remarkable cures performed solely by such medicines.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 110 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.W. for Benjamin Billingsley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: W.W.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to William Walwyn. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.); Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65062:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TOUCH-STONE FOR Phyſick, Directing By evident Marks and Characters to ſuch Medicines, AS Without Purgers, Vomiters, Bleedings, Iſſues, Minerals; or any other diſturbers of Nature, may be ſecurely truſted for Cure in all extreamities, AND Be eaſily diſtinguiſhed from ſuch as are hazardous or dangerous: Exemplyfied By various Inſtances of Remarkable Cures performed ſolely by ſuch Medicines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. W.</hi> for <hi>Benjamin Billingſley,</hi> at <hi>Greſham-Colledge</hi>-gate, near the Church in <hi>Broad</hi>-ſtreet 1667</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:65062:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65062:2"/>
            <head>To the Ingenious Reader.</head>
            <p>SInce the generous breeding of moſt Phyſitians, in reaſon may be preſumed to have freed them, more from envy and partiallity, then leſs Phyloſophical profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; though here and there ſome few may appear perverſe: yet now there ſeemeth no cauſe to doubt their ready and cheerful entertainment, of whatſoever can be propoſed for ſupport of humane frailty, or relief of diſtreſſed patients, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe of their frequent, and free converſe with the moſt noble <hi>Virtuoſi,</hi> thoſe ample encouragers of all improving Studies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65062:3"/>
            <p>The ſcruple being rather, how this Diſcourſe will be diſgeſted by thoſe who are furniſhers of all ſorts of ingredients; and alſo by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parers of Medicines: for ſince ſelf denial, may not like their <hi>Semper vivum</hi> be alwaies green and floriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. If it cannot be proved, that both ſhall be no loſers; how can it be expected they ſhould freely yeild to ſuch an alteration, as this Touchſtone imports, though the whole Society of practiſers ſhould deem it requiſite.</p>
            <p>For abatement therefore, of any proneſs to oppoſition, it may be needful to give this aſſurance to all thoſe, who furniſh either forraign or domeſtick materials, that in this
<pb facs="tcp:65062:3"/> ſublime and more refined way of Medicine; not leſs but much larger quantities, are likely to be uſed, in that where much can yeild but very little, much of neceſſity muſt be employed.</p>
            <p>Then for the preparers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighers of Medicines, between Phyſitians and Patients: were all expreſsly to be regulated, according to the Marks and Characters here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſpecified, no loſs at all appeareth; for in this pure, liquid, powerful, pleaſant and durable way; not one ſpoonful would ever periſh or decay upon their hands: neither Time, nor Winters cold, nor Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers heat, in the leaſt impairing their virtue or efficacy: a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe
<pb facs="tcp:65062:4"/> far ſurmounting all objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if what they yearly loſe by periſhable ware, be but duely weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Nor is this new way leſs vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative of their reputation, not only ſeldomer failing of their deſired ſucceſs in Cure, but not the leaſt quantity ever caſt away by their Patients, being ſuch as is ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to them ſundry waies, which how many hundreds if not thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of pounds would be ſaved yearly in Patients purſes, may be worth their conſideration, nor is there many of their preſent prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, but what by ſolicitous Study, and ingenious Art, may be converted into this clear ſtream of Phyſick.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65062:4"/>
            <p>Beſides, where one now in the preſent way of Medicine they are in, makes uſe either of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians advice, or of any other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations; and when they do, do it but meerly for neceſſity, as dreading the trouble, tediouſneſs, and danger thereof, well nigh as much as ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it: In this pure, pleaſant, and ſafe effectuall way, twenty at the leaſt would be frequent and familiar therewith, no time of the year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unſeaſonable, no ſcrupuloſity in the dyet, no pains nor gripes in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, nor tireſome confinement, to houſe or chamber, (unleſs when extreamity enforceth) nay when they are proper for all perſons in all weakneſſes, and diſtempers, from
<pb facs="tcp:65062:5"/> the Cradle to the oldeſt age: may be alſo taken in Dyet for improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, and in Recreation as the moſt pleaſant and reviving re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, what infinite quantities muſt neceſſarily be employed.</p>
            <p>So that they could not but be vaſt gainers every way, both in profit and credit, by ſo happy an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, bringing alſo to the Phyſitian, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the reſpects and rewards uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, if not more and greater.</p>
            <p>The ineſtimable contentment of a quiet mind, reſting ſecurely and calmly amidſt all occaſions and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamities, with this ſweet repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that he runs no hazard with his Patients, and yet ſupplies them with the utmoſt helps imaginable: ſo
<pb facs="tcp:65062:5"/> that both the Phyſitian, the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Materials, and the preparer of Medicines, are all in an aſſured con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, unto whom I wiſh one more were added, ſo far am I from deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the prejudice of any: And that is <hi>Studiers</hi> and <hi>Inventers</hi> of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, known only by their faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the fruit of their producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: To be encouraged therein, and not to be diverted with any other part of Phyſick, or Practiſe; for if truly ſuch, they will never be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, nor deſire any other buſineſs, being not ſuch by Education, but by Birth and Nature; for ſome Title whereunto I appeal, to the juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration of the pallat, to its pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine juriſdiction, in diſcerning
<pb facs="tcp:65062:6"/> Virtues, and choiſe of Materials: And to the ſucceſſeful conception and appropriation of the true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane temperature, that <hi>Clavis Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinae,</hi> not conſiſting in the equality of the Elements or Humors (as moſt may imagine) but in the Proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Coherence of the ſpirit, and all parts of the Medicine, with the ſpirit of the true Humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; without which, thoſe who traffick for Medicine, may be as coaſters; but no conſiderable new diſcoverers: This being to the Arts advancement, like <hi>Columbus</hi> his card to his diſcovery of the <hi>Indies,</hi> who though long ſeeming but as a vain boaſter, yet thoſe who firſt gave credit found it, far exceeding
<pb facs="tcp:65062:6"/> his report; and ſo I doubt not it will prove here, the Medicines herein propoſed for an example, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doing harm, but good where ever they were taken, many wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had known them ſooner, never any repenting their uſe: And if the Body be more worth then Rayment, and Health to be preferred before Riches, it being not in Mountains of Gold, to give that exemption from the pains, fears and miſeries of ſickneſs, which reſides in a benign powerful Medicine; your good acceptance of theſe overtures, will never blemiſh either that Virtue or that Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, for which you will be ever highly honored,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By Your Moſt humble Servant,</hi> W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:65062:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65062:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Preface To the Reader.</head>
            <p>IT being uſual for Authors in Prefaces to render an account of the occaſion which gave Birth to their writings, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> acquaint the Reader with the deſign or ſcope of their Diſcourſes, I thought it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to continue a cuſtom approved by many Illuſtrious examples.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65062:8"/>
            <p>Let me therefore give thee to underſtand, that it is not deſire of applauſe hath engaged me in this Controverſie. The care I have taken to conceal my Name will, I ſuppoſe, free me from ſuch ſuſpicion; but beſides, let me aſſure thee I am too far from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing my ſelf any addition to my Repute from this ſcrible, That I do rather apprehend it will leſſen my Esteem with many of thoſe excellent Perſons, who are now pleaſed to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me with their Friendſhip: and do expect from me Diſcourſes very different from thoſe I here preſent thee. Which conſiderations ſurely will gain me credit, when I affirm That no Motive beſides that of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb facs="tcp:65062:8"/> advantage could ever havepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon me, to exchange my dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Studies of Experimental Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and Phyſick (moſt pleaſing and profitable imployments) for barren Controverſie, which I ever declined. And among all, if I had conſulted my own quiet or Intereſt, I ſhould have avoyded this wherein I have now engaged; which may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion me much trouble, but cannot poſſibly bring me any advantage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that ſatisfaction which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the reſult of Actions well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. Which pleaſure I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs will be much heightned, if this endeavour of mine meets with good entertainment and work the deſired Effect; which that it may have, I
<pb facs="tcp:65062:9"/> will particularly addreſs my ſelf to all the Perſons concern'd with me in this debate: Who are the People or Patients, and Phyſicians.</p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe is chiefly intended for the Firſt, it being they, who are moſt highly injured by the unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable practices of thoſe we have therein accuſed; for although many underſtanding Perſons among the People are ſufficiently ſenſible of the abuſes we have manifeſted; and that it is of abſolute neceſſity ſome reformation be made: yet all are not thus perſwaded, for we may dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerve, that many who are leſs diſcerning, being deceived by an imaginary good, covet their own ruins; and unleſs they be given to
<pb facs="tcp:65062:9"/> underſtand which is the evil and which the good, by perſons in whom they have reaſon to confide, they muſt neceſſarily run much hazard. I have here endeavoured to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, which I ſhould diſpair of, did I only foreſee inconveniences a far off (the Vulgar being led by ſenſe, and not by probable conject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures) but ſince they do now actually labour under many, and thoſe obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inconveniences, how ſhort ſoever their ſight be, the ſenſe of feeling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no leſs acute in them, than in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers I perſwade my ſelf they will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilygive their aſſent to thoſe Truths I have here diſcovered. Now there are many things whereof moſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries are highly guilty, as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs,
<pb facs="tcp:65062:10"/> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskilfulneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs on the one hand, and Intruſion into the Phyſicians Imployment (I mean the Practice of Phyſick) on the other: on all which accounts as I have fully demonſtrated, they are exceedingly injurious to the Publick. In order to the prevention of ſuch unpardonable abuſes of the People I have made this Propoſal, That Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians prepare and diſpence their own Medicines; and at large ſhewed That the advantages of ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution will be manyand great. <hi>For it will much abate the charge and expence of Phyſick, and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines themſelves will be more ſafe and effectual than now they are, intereſt obliging Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb facs="tcp:65062:10"/> to have their Phyſick as good as they can contrive or prepare; and certainly ſuch a State of Phyſick of all other is moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable, wherein no man having the Intereſt can have the Power, nor any having the Power can have the Intereſt to prepare Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines unfaithfully: wherein bad men ſhall be made good, and thoſe that are good never be tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pted to become diſhoneſt. And in that Conſtitution of Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy for which we contend, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe men be never ſo bad; yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs their wickedneſs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have any ill influence on Phyſick,</hi> as is manifeſted at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in this following Diſcourſe: ſo
<pb facs="tcp:65062:11"/> if the ſick have regard, either to profit or ſafety, they will addreſs themſelves to thoſe Perſons who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them with the beſt Remedies, and at cheapeſt Rates.</p>
            <p>And as for Phyſicians, they muſt neceſſarily put their affaires into ſome ſuch Method, as this we have commended; If they have any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for their Patients, or intend to improve Pharmacy it ſelf. For as it hath been well obſerved, if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend only upon that we read in Books, we ſhall never promote this Art beyond its preſent limits; and if Phyſicians in former times had not been knowing in Simples, examined their Vertues, and Tempers, enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into their Effects, and mixed
<pb facs="tcp:65062:11"/> them with their own hands, there had been no ſuch Science as Phyſick. Now according to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Axiom, <hi>Ex quibus Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ex iiſdem Nutrimur,</hi> Thoſe things which gave a being to this Noble faculty muſt help to make it compleat; towards which as nothing can contribute more than the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Pharmacy: ſo neither can any thing promote that, more than Phyſicians taking it into their Management. But beſides all this, it is fit that they who <hi>exerciſe</hi> themſelves in the Practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, be ſatisfied their Medicines are good; whereby their Mind will be free, and without any clog: which would add more difficulties and
<pb facs="tcp:65062:12"/> dangers to a thing by it ſelf hard and dangerous.</p>
            <p>Theſe and other Conſiderations mentioned and inſiſted on in the following Diſcourſe will I aſſure my ſelf, perſwade all Phyſicians who have reſpect to the good and benefit of their Patients, Honour of their inrofeſſion, or own Reputation, to put Pharmacy into other hands, and into better Methods, than thoſe wherein at preſent it is; Whereby they who now diſhonour it (I mean the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries) will either be reduced to a ſenſe and performance of their Duty, or ſufficiently puniſhed. For Notwithſtanding that they do now <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimouſly reſolve with aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted endeavours to Oppoſe all Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation;
<pb facs="tcp:65062:12"/> yet I am perſwaded that if Phyſicians take ſome ſuch courſes as thoſe I have mentioned, the event will be the ſamewith that of Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Where if the Commande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute he makes ſome of the Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers exemplary, and threatens o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; of fierce, that they were in general, each one out of his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Fear becomes obedient: So how inſolent ſoever the Apothecaries now are when they ſee their Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment neer and certain, not truſting to one another, they will haſten all to Obedience; eſpecially if good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement be given to thoſe who return to their Duty, and become Reformadoes.</p>
            <p>And now (to haſten to a Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion)
<pb facs="tcp:65062:13"/> if any fancy, we have too rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attaqued the Apothecaries, let them conſider (and then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they will excuſe us) that what we have done is only in our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; for we had never interrupted their quiet, could they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained themſelves within due limits and not invaded our Profeſſion. So that if the Caſe be ſtated rightly, it will appear moſt evident, that we are on the Defenſive part, They the Aggreſſors; and that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtly be blamed, if in our own Defence we offend them: or if being forced, we take violent Courſes, whoſe End yet is not (as may be pretended) Deſtruction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, but Order and redreſs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65062:13"/>
            <p>Nothing now remains but that I Apologize for the defects of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Diſcourſe. It may be objected, that the Method is not exact, the expreſſion rude, the Style unpoliſhed and abrupt, the parts not cloſly cemented by handſom and ſutable Tranſitions. All which I readily acknowledge: But withall Deſire the Readers to conſider that this Book was begun and finiſhed within the ſpace of ſix or eight dayes at the moſt; and even then I was not free from diverſions of many kinds: ſo that being penned in ſo ſhort a time, the ſubject it ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant, and the writer variouſly diſtracted, it is ſcarcely poſſible it ſhould be compleat in Method or
<pb facs="tcp:65062:14"/> Expreſſion. Beſides, this Diſcourſe was not calculated for Scholars, but for the Vulgar to whoſe capacity it is adapted; for if I had intended to inſtruct the former, I would have taken more time and pains, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted the matter better, diſpoſed it more advantageouſly, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to cloath it in more handſome expreſſions.</p>
            <p>I muſt not here forget to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that I have borrowed ſeveral paſſages from the judicious Author of a late excellent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe concerning the State of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and the regulation of its Practice. I ſuppoſe it will be eaſily imagined that I could have ſpoken the ſame things in other words; but
<pb facs="tcp:65062:14"/> my reſpect for that Worthy Perſon diſpoſes me to believe they will ſound better and be more effectual in his own language; although I muſt crave his pardon for tranſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſome, and accommodating o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to a propoſal, he did not then think fit to mention.</p>
            <p>For Faults in Printing &amp;c. the Printer muſt be reſponſible; and particularly for that formall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the 177. Page, which was never ſo intended by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
            <p>This is all with which I thought fit to acquaint thee, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now end with this requeſt. That thou determine nothing in the behalf, or to the prejudice of this
<pb facs="tcp:65062:15"/> performance, till thou haſt imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally examined all that is contained therein; and then if it appear that I have ſpoken truth, I expect it ſhould be owned and promoted by thee: if I be in any thing miſtaken I am content to hear of it, and ready to retract whatſoever is not conſonant to Truth and Reaſon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65062:15"/>
            <head>A TOUCH-STONE FOR PHYSICK, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1-49" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough of all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Sciences, that of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the Medicinal part is of moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to Humane Happineſs: yet is there hardly any Art, Science or My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, whether for Delight, Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65062:16"/> or Neceſſity, but what hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſtart thereof, by many degrees, of real Improvement; Whilſt <hi>Phyſick,</hi> the chief of Arts, inſtituted for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Man's health, without which all his felicity in a moment is turned into gall and bitterneſs; hath ſo little to glory in, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infinite endeavours of the ſtudious, with the utmoſt help of Chymiſtry; the mok skilfull do ingenuouſly confeſs, They believe the far better part reſts ſtill undiſcovered.</p>
               <p>A Truth too evident, and the ſad cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thereof too manifeſt to be doubted; yet ſo accompanied with unpleaſing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, both upon the Speculative, Inventive and Practick part, that I willingly decline all repetition of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever upon my enquiry fell into obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>Onely as to the moſt Important, and which render'd the whole Fabrick craz'd and tottering: I muſt needs ſay, That
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65062:16"/> to my Apprehenſion, the aims of the Studious, Inquiſitive after the Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation or Reſtauration of <hi>Man,</hi> the ſole Subject of Phyſick, had not been taken aright, nor in due meaſure proportioned to ſo peculiar and ſo refin'd a Being.</p>
               <p>For, permitting my Underſtanding its free courſe throughout the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Phyſical Notions; at length my thoughts thus fixed: That the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal conſtitution of Humane Nature, being at firſt but One, however ſince deviated into various Temperatures and Complexions; and being far more ſublimed, than any other Creature on Earth, to render his Body a fit Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his Divine contemplative and diſcourſive Soul. The whole maſs of aſſiſtants aſſigned by this Art, for his ſupportation or recovery, appeared ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo weak and impotent; or elſe ſo courſe, caſual, violent and dangerous; as ſeemed very unſuitable ſo ſublime a Nature.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65062:17"/>
               <p>Upon which, I conceived it unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably requiſite, that all proviſions and preparations deſigned for help of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ought in ſpecial manner, both in purity, efficacie and pregnancy, to hold due and juſt proportion to the peculiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the true Humane Temperature or Conſtitution: and that all adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a groſs, impure, or improper, unbenign nature, muſt needs produce croſs and perverſe effects; and could not but be the main occaſion of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold failings and miſcarriages ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and apparently diſcernable in Phyſick.</p>
               <p>With which concluſion being very much ſatisfied; my hopes ſoon led me into perſuaſions of a poſſibility of rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing new ayds both to Diet and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, ſo refined, and ſo ſuited to the true Humane Conſtitution, and ſo appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to diſtinct Infirmities, Diſtempers, and Diſeaſes; that, adminiſter'd in any caſe, and to any complexion, though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65062:17"/> never ſo far diſtant from the original: ſhould really intend its reduction, and without any diſturbance of Nature, by Looſners, Vomiters, Bleedings, Iſſues, Shaving the head, Cliſters, Bliſters; and without Minerals, or any hazardous or nauſeous Ingredients; might ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally be relyed on in all extremities: And this ſolely from their powerfull friendlineſs to Humane Nature, and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious virtue in extinguiſhing the veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous cauſes of Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>In purſuance whereof, depending ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much upon my palate, long exerciſed in determining of Virtues, (by which, Compounds, as well as Simples, became equally liable to my aſſiſtance;) and preſſed thereunto by an expreſs propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity in Nature: In proceſs of time I proved ſo ſuccesful in choice of mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, and in heightning and uniting of Excellencies; as by degrees to raiſe a large variety of ſo kindly and ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Medicines, That not onely have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65062:18"/> themſelves ſerviceable to the Healthful in Diet and Refreſhment; and to the weakeſt women and children in manifold infirmities; but in greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, (all other means failing) have frequently been prevalent, beyond all hope or expectation; and this too (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my ayms) without any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Violence or inward Diſturbance of the body, either by Vomiters, Looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Minerals, or any other Diſturbers of Nature.</p>
               <p>Inſomuch that their various, weighty and remarkable performances have long time repreſented their peculiar qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, as ſo many evident marks and characters of Real Medicine, whereby to diſtinguiſh ſuch as are (from ſuch as are not) to be truſted in cure, or fit for Humane Conſtitutions.</p>
               <p>And to my own particular; ever ſince I underſtood them, they have ſerved me as a real Teſt or <hi>Touchſtone</hi> of Medicine; uſing no other, for any that rely on me
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65062:18"/> in any occaſion, but Medicines of their qualities; wherein having been ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful, to my own ſatisfaction, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers approbation, yea even to admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I have thence entertained ſome apprehenſions, that it could not be taken amiſs, but rather as a fair progreſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Arts Improvement, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh theſe Marks and Characters, as a competent <hi>Touchſtone</hi> for probation of Medicine in general; eſpecially of my own; and thereby poſſibly come to be ſomewhat better underſtood, as to my Phyſical Conceptions, than hitherto I have been; ſome having been over for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to imagine, all I aymed at, or had attained, amounted to no more, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome pleaſant preparations and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, ſerving merely for Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Recreation, without any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial effect or prevalencie upon Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Diſeaſes. Whether it be ſo or not, and how far they are miſtaken, who thus cenſure, the whole Diſcourſe will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65062:19"/> plainly evince: and haply may prove a ſafe and ſure Guide to diſtreſſed Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, what kinde of Medicines to avoid, and what to embrace, in any their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Marks and Characters, with their Grounds or Reaſons annexed, are as followeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AS, Firſt, I conceive, a benign kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Medicine ought to be <hi>Liquid:</hi> and this, for avoyding that difficulty and diſturbance incident in the diſge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of thoſe of groſſer ſubſtances; and likewiſe for the evil conſequence of their remaining earthy parts in the coats, films and crevices both of the ſtomach and bowels, which generally ſo clog and tire the natural faculties to expell them; as inſtead of that quiet and ready help requiſite in Sickneſs, makes Nature a new and tedious work in their avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; as whoever notes ſhall find in a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65062:19"/> ſad dejection of Spirit when they have done their beſt. Whereas things <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid,</hi> if milde, diſturbe no part, puts Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to no ſtreſs in ordering them to its beſt advantage, nor leaves any remains for after Inconveniences: but through their gentle Vivacity, and inſinuative Virtues, (like the Waters of Life) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately proſecute the prime End for which they were taken.</p>
               <p>II. I conceive they ought not onely to be <hi>Liquid,</hi> but <hi>tranſparently clear and pure, exempt from all groſſneſs of reſidence or taint of rankneſs.</hi> It being poſſible to have liquid things as bright and clear as Chryſtal, which yet in ſmell no carrion ever exceeded in noyſomneſs; a tang whereof, any one that notes will find, in moſt of what is uſed for Refreſhment or for Relief, in firſt Illneſs. Which ſhould be heedfully avoided, becauſe by things courſe, rank, or tainted, the whole ſourſe of Blond and Spirits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inſenſibly to be corrupted; all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65062:20"/> faculties debilitated; and the beſt and ſtrongeſt conſtitutions, by degrees, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed into the worſt diſtempers; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, like Virtues deſcending from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, they ought to be immaculately clear and pure.</p>
               <p>III. Such Medicines as may be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in cure, I conceive, ought, as much as is poſſible, to be <hi>Pleaſant</hi> and to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in <hi>ſmall quantity;</hi> that they may not in the leaſt be burdenſom, but at firſt touch appear like true and chearfull friends, that make the diſtreſſed heart leap for joy; no ſooner taſted, but Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bids them welcom, and eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes them to their proper ſervice. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; jucundum, as in Divine benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, being never to be ſeparated in Phyſick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IV. Such Medicines with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent qualities, ought eſpecially to be highly virtuous and powerfull, and which at firſt taſt, by their lively, ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ightly, yet milde quickneſs, ſhould
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65062:20"/> evidently appear ſuch ſtout, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breath'd valiant Champions, as are tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly qualified to tug grapple with, and ſubdue the moſt violent, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous, peſtilential enemies of Mans Health and happineſs: And yet withall ſo milde, gentle and manageable, (like our bleſſed Lamb and Lion couched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) as Children in greateſt weakneſs may partake with ſafety; and for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that they are ſuch, the preſcribers, if deſired, are to take the like quantity in ſight of the Patient or Relations, for the more undoubted aſſurance of its inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and that it partakes not of any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous ingredient.</p>
               <p>V. Such Medicines as may comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably be relyed on in cure and in caſes of extremity, ought to be ſo truly friendly to Humane Nature, that if taken by man, woman or childe, in health, ſhall no ways move their bodies, but ſhall nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and ſtrengthen them: and yet if by any in Sickneſs, the very ſame Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65062:21"/> taken in the ſame quantity, ſhall in due time either open or binde, vomit or ſtop vomiting, ſweat or reſtrain ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, give ſleep or abate exceſſive ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; as the inſtant neceſſity of the body moſt requireth, or moſt conduceth to recovery. And this, as the moſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing character, I conceive, is moſt to be noted by the Ingenious, and to be inſiſted on: For how can that poſſibly appear truly to deſerve the Name of a Medicine, or real helper of the ſick, or be rationally deem'd to work upon a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper; which, if given to a well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhall either binde or looſen him, vomit, or ſweat, or lay him aſleep, even as it doth thoſe who are ſick? and which if given to never ſo ſound a perſon in larger quantity, ſhall purge him, or vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him into his grave, ſweat out his laſt breath, or ſleep him paſt ever waking to this life; which are the known qualities of moſt things given in Sickneſs: So as with much more likelihood they might
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65062:21"/> be ſtiled Diſturbers of Nature, (for how elſe do they thus work upon the health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full?) rather than Medicines and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Helpers, whoſe good qualities are with tenderneſs to cheriſh and retain all that's good in the body, and without the hazardous violences of Purgers, Vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Bleedings, Iſſues, Shaving the head, Cliſters, or Bliſters; and without Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, or other nauſeous or dangerous Ingredients, to exclude onely what is evil; and not, <hi>Bedlam</hi>-like, turn good to bad, and then madly throw out all together; which are the properties not of Heavenly and peaceable, but of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal wrathful Spirits.</p>
               <p>VI. And laſtly, Such Medicines as may be juſtly relyed on in cure, that they may be known to be compleat, ought not to be periſhable Commodities, which argues ſuch defects, as renders them unlikely to hold out upon a long march; being apt to tire, grow faint, ſick, weak and heartleſs, before, or when
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65062:22"/> they come in ſight of, or near the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, therefore they ought not to want this ſure Mark, (Cloſe ſtopt) to keep Good for Years (in all Climates) and in full ſtrength and vigour without any the leaſt diminution; much after the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of an endleſs life, which is no ſmall aſſurance of their real virtue and efficacy. Then having all the other precedent qualities conjoyned in every medicine; and a large variety of them, (variety being ſingularly uſeful) you have medicines moſt Maſculine and Heroick, ſuch as may confidently be relied on for Cure, and be eaſily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from thoſe which are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous, or dangerous.</p>
               <p>All which being neither difficult to remember; nor hard to be underſtood; and ſuch as cannot be denyed to be both pertinent and ſufficient for proof and aſſurance of Medicine: Admit patients and all the Ingenious every where ſhould henceforth hold Practitioners
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65062:22"/> ſtrictly to theſe Characters; accepting or refuſing; accordingly: what a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Improvement w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld it ſoon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in Phyſick: By neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing all Students and Practitioners, to ſet themſelves to that which the Noble <hi>Hippocrates</hi> made the chief Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Phyſician worthy Eſtimation Viz. <hi>By Study and his own Induſtry, to bring to light ſomething that was not known before, and better known than unknown, or at leaſt to perfect ſomething that was imperfect before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then as Excellencies for real uſe in Phyſick could not but every where abound; ſo would ſuch a Teſt eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, naturally tend to the fixation of this too much uncertain Art; put a period to the many Contrarieties and Contradictions of Practitioners, be an occaſion of leſs harm and danger, of more pertinency, certainty, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity in Cure: and abundantly more enable them to perform with Comfort
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65062:23"/> the infinite truſt repoſed in them, eſpecially by their more Ingenious and Noble Patients in their extremities.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Marks and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters conceived requiſite for the teſt of Medicine; and the deſirable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which in good probability would enſue upon ſuch an eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Nor let any ſuppoſe, as ſome may be apt to do, (who are loath any thing ſhould prove of weight, but what they themſelves diſcover) that theſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters or Marks of real Medicine are but meer impracticable notions, ſet forth to amuſe the credulous with wonders that never were nor never will be found in medicine: For ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all ſuch ſlight ſuggeſtions, ſince ſuch medicines are beſt known by their Fruits: It will be beſt and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to let them ſpeak for themſelves in ſome of their many fold inſtances of Cures performed by them, in various
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65062:23"/> and dangerous caſes: and are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>The firſt of which, is of a man of middle age, afflicted with ſo extream a Bloody Flux as was deemed incurable, yet he perfectly recovered by two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a medicine, every way anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Characters; being a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful ſubduer of thoſe venoms which occaſion ſuch diſtempers.</p>
               <p>Another is of one about 50: who had been long ill, but being of a ſtrong conſtitution, thought with help of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary means to wear it out: As the manner of many hath been, till the beſt comes too late; and they wear themſelves into their Graves, as it was like to have proved with him; for when my adviſe was firſt deſired, he was ſore all over his body, light hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſpots upon his breaſt, very fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh, and ſwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in his legg: other adviſe he had which ordered him to bleed; which he not likeing, he fell
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65062:24"/> under my Charge, and in leſs then eight dayes time, by the ſole help of Medicines of the ſame nature, perfectly recovered.</p>
               <p>Another is of a Gentleman about 30. long and grievouſly tormented with an Ague: both hot and cold fitts; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently painful, with extream thirſt, and ſoreneſs of throat; who after much time and money ſpent in vain, being plied with ſome variety of theſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, became perfectly well. In which caſe as the variety proved very acceptable, ſo proves it Generally very ſucceſsful in all or moſt diſtempers.</p>
               <p>Another is of a young Gentleman, who upon an extream Cold and ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all over his body falling into a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent vomiting, and looſeneſs; which increaſing under much means of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, I was importun'd to take care of him; and in leſs than a weeks time he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, ſolely by the uſe of divers of theſe Medicines.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:65062:24"/>
               <p>Another inſtance is of a Gentleman ſomewhat above fifty: ſurpriſed with a violent ſurfeit, and its worſt effects, excream vomiting, headach, high feaver, and ſoreneſs every where: and which notwithſtanding many conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and thereupon bleedings, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, vomitings, often repeated: with ſundry the beſt reputed Julips and Cordials uſuall in ſuch caſes: neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſettled into ſix hours cold fits, with tortures in his knees and ancles as if upon the Rack, and near upon ten houres hot fitts, his breaſt ſtuffed with tough and clammy phlegme, throat ſwoln and bliſter'd, his tongue parcht, ſcurft, raw and ſo big that he could hardly ſpeak a word to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
               <p>In this woful plight, his Phyſicians, Himſelf and Relations quite hopeleſs, hearing what had been performed by my Medicines, I was ſent for: yet not without much ſcruple, as one that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65062:25"/> gave chiefly Spirits and hot things: which this Gentleman ſaid, How to one in ſuch a flame as he was in, Spirits and hot things could be proper, he could not underſtand: I replied, he would ſoon finde there was a benigne as well as a venomous heat, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he had too much of the one, but too little of the other; And that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſupplies of the better, his Lamp of Life could not be long maintained.</p>
               <p>Which yet I perceived he ſo ſlowly admitted, that I was leaving of him: but his Lady taking me aſide, and asking me whether I thought there was any poſſibility of his recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: I told her I did believe there was: ſhe asked me by what means, there having been ſo much uſed and failed: I ſaid by Cordial Medicines: ſhe ſaid he would not endure any thing that was hot, I told her it was impoſſible without it: But yet ſuch heaters as would certainly cool him: ſhe asktme
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65062:25"/> if I had any ſuch, I told her I would have none elſe, nor valued any other.</p>
               <p>Which ſo far prevailed that he took that Night two ounces of one of my Medicines, and ſo did conſtantly of that or ſome other, alwayes before his cold fit; and at the end of it, reſpecting his hot fitt, both which with all their painful threatning effects were after a while much mitigated, and in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion moſt happily extinguiſhed. And had been ſooner but for the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate interpoſition of a gentle Purger; which becauſe of Coſtivenes was preſt upon him by one of his Phyſicians, who generally make ſuch a doo about keeping the body ſolluble, as ſpoiles all too often. This Purge though of the middle ſort, (which I muſt not know of at no hand) gave him upon twenty ſtooles, and ſo chearful he was upon it, that they reckoned now all filth was purged and carried out of his body: Inſomuch as when I came amongſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65062:26"/> them, all eyes were cloudy upon me; ſo I ſaid little, and off I went: But before next morning the Scene was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and I haſtily ſent for, his cold and hot fits being doubled both in time and extremity; And he ſo wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened as they all feared his ſudden diſſolution: Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> falling to work a freſh with the ſame Medicines, though this miſchievous looſener ſet us back at leaſt ten Cordials, yet it was not longe're all was perfected, wherein our pleaſant varlety proved infinitely Advantageous and Contentful.</p>
               <p>For ſo clear a Convert this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man became, that though at firſt any thing of heat frightned him, yet ſo throughly reconciled to my heaters was he, that not onely all his Cordials were freely taken by him, but for one of them, (which hath heat enough in it to ſtartle moſt practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers) he would not be without a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and not onely ſipping of it, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65062:26"/> drinking of it continually night and day, ſo much more eaſie is it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince an ingenious Gentleman (with whom Reaſon and Experience ſoon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail) rather then Capricious Arts-men, whoſe too much ſelf-reſpect, or errour in breeding ſway them, one while to accuſe thoſe Medicines of deficiency becauſe of their mildneſs, another while of danger becauſe of their heat: And indeed Generally to adhere to old and miſtaken Maxims.</p>
               <p>For ſo in this caſe when the Cure was almoſt finiſhed, comes one, who finding by all was done he had never ſweat, Raſhly pronounces, Then he could not Live. And ſo in all haſt writ a large Receipt to enforce a ſweat, <hi>a Mineral therein</hi> being the main Agent depended on for producing the effect. But the Gentleman was more wary than to take it, and ſo contrary to his ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Aphoriſm, recovered without once Sweating in all the time of his ſickneſs,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65062:27"/> and in reaſon may ſomwhat reſtrain the too frequent interpoſing of Arts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endants with their vulgar opinions: For of all who have relied upon theſe Medicines, none ever miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried but two: the one by the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate obtruſion of a Looſener; and the other by the unkindneſs of a far ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Brother which in ſickneſs proves mortal like a venomous Damp.</p>
               <p>My next inſtance is of one naturally of a good Conſtitution, and Chearful, whoſe occaſions inducing his too much converſe with Wine, in proceſs of time inclining to the Dropſie, and in fine ſwelled his belly, took away his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, ſometimes he had ſtoppage of his Urine, and ſometimes made reddiſh water, under which Infirmities he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained long, though he uſed the beſt counſel and Phyſick he could get; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of amendment, fell into other extreames; for his fleſh every way aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, his ſtrength utterly failed, his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65062:27"/> belly ſunk and clung'd to his back, no ſtools but by Gliſters, nor could he eat one bit of fleſh-meat at any rate, nor ought elſe but as he forc't it down. In this ſad plight he deſired my aſſiſtance, and in fourteen dayes with medicines of this kind onely, his appetite and digeſture were reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, his ſtrength reſtored, his fleſh and countenance well likeing, his belly in due ſtate, his urine and ſtools naturall and he ſo blyth &amp; jocund as was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to all that knew him, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for above four months: But his occaſions ſtill miſleading of him; and upon a frolick overgoing his ſtrength he fell ill again, and then unhappily waving the means which had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly helpt him, took a reſolution to be his own Phyſician, by help of ſuch Books as were then in repute, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he tamper'd ſo long till he was paſt recovery, his Diſtempers being far above the reach of Book or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Medicine.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:65062:28"/>
               <p>The next is of a Gentlewoman long under Phyſick for Diſtempers of the Breaſt, as Cough, ſhortneſs of Breath, Feaveriſh, extreamly waſted in body, and ſunk in Spirits, hardly eating or drinking but what ſhe vomited purged; and vomited and bled, ſhe had been with Iſſues, and her head ſhaved, and ſo left hopeleſs, unleſs by Countrey air in the Spring. This being the beginning of Winter, many queſtions and much diſcourſe I had from her, as whether I had ever ſeen any one in her diſtemper, or had ever cured any: Alſo what means I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; ſeeing as able Phyſicians as <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> yielded prevailed not: I told her 'twas not my way to ſpeak either of my Experience or Performance, that if the party who adviſed her to ſend for me had not ſatisfied her therein: And withal, that I was not apt to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, but where I had ample hopes of Cure, he was too blame. And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65062:28"/> that I did believe and was well aſſured that there was both more proper and more powerful means in being, than Phyſicians were uſually acquainted with; and by which with Gods bleſſing, I did not doubt to cure her, as hopeleſs as ſhe was, without either purging, or vomiting, or bleeding, or iſſues, wiſhing alſo her Hair had been ſpared, as the chief comfort of ſo weak a Head, with this ſhe chear'd a little.</p>
               <p>So I fell to work with my real Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, and in few weeks time ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, as that ſhe frequently went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad that Winter: nor kept ſhe houſe any more on this occaſion,</p>
               <p>Another Inſtance is of a Girle about four yeares old, that by a Feaver and Conſumption, and much Roving Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick was in a hopeleſs condition, yet in a weeks time by theſe Medicines onely, perfectly recovered.</p>
               <p>A young Gentleman came to me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout noon with an Ague moſt terribly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65062:29"/> ſhaking him, to whom I immediatly gave half a Pinte of one of my Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines well heated, which was the uſual way by which in the great Ague Year abundance were cured: He drank it off at two draughts, and it ſtayed with him, but within a quarter of an hour it made him vomit very largely, and thereupon he became inſtantly ſo well, as I would have had him dine with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but excuſing himſelf he fell faſt a ſleep for two hours, and never had the leaſt Grudgings after it; which is the more to be noted, becauſe it's frequent with the ſame Medicine to ſtay vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings when the body any wayes ſtands in need thereof.</p>
               <p>A young Maiden much depreſſed in Spirit, and ſwoln in body by unkindly Obſtructions, which ſhe could finde no means to diſſolve, upon the uſe of one of theſe Medicines appropriate to thoſe diſtempers, perfectly recovered.</p>
               <p>A middle aged Woman, troubled
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65062:29"/> grievouſly with Hyſtericall diſtempers taking a good quantity of a Medicin thereto appropriate, recovered; as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance more have done, by the ſame and the like means: for in this, as in moſt other Diſtempers, Variety proves of very abſolute advantage.</p>
               <p>Alſo a young Lad, lying more like a dead than a living childe; taking a ſmall quantity of one of the Medicines for that purpoſe, in ſhort time voyded Wormes and recovered, as many others alſo have done, who have been thought to have had Wormes though they voyded none.</p>
               <p>A young man being in a tedious Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and finding no relief in much Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick uſed to him; a friend of his ſent him often ſmall quantities of my Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which thoſe with whom he was, ſcrupled to let him take; being told, they were too hot, and altogether unfit for him in his caſe, which was near unto a Pleureſie: Yet doing all they other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65062:30"/> could, growing worſe and worſe, his friends urg'd him to remove to their houſe; which being done, weak and ill as he was, and he then plied a while with diverſe of them, his Cure came on very fairly. But on a ſudden was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt choak't with a maſs of thick putrid phlegm, which yet, ſipping upon a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine peculiar thereunto, for ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance; it ſo ripened, raiſed, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expell'd it, (as is uſual with it in all caſes of phlegm) that he inſtantly and perfectly recovered.</p>
               <p>Another Inſtance is of a Gentleman, who with his Lady being in Town up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Law occaſions in height of Summer, fell into an extreme Fever: She having had full knowledg of the recovery of ſome of her friends, by the uſe of my Medicines, when all other means prov'd fruitleſs; She of her ſelf ſingled out one of them, which upon occaſion ſhe had uſed her ſelf alſo; and ſo poſſeſt her Husband with confidence therein, that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65062:30"/> he ſolely relyed thereupon, and with the expenſe of about three Pints of it, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly recovered: and which hath drawn their affections ſo towards it, that they have had often of it, and diverſe others of them, for their Family occaſions.</p>
               <p>Another is of One ſome Thirty miles from <hi>London,</hi> long tired with a violent Fever, that admitted no check by the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavours of a skilful Phyſician; but having formerly had good experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of my Medicines, withſtood all denyal, and haſted a friend to me for a Pint of one of my Medicines, which he named, and a ſmall quantity of another, and what elſe I would ſend him: So, I ſent him the Pint of the firſt he nam'd, and ſix Ounces of the next, and as much of another, and three Ounces of a fourth ſort; which being ſoon with him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many cautions were given him, in reſpect of their heat, he being, as was told him, ſcorch'd and ſcalded from the tip of his tongue down to his Navel; yet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65062:31"/> being ſure of what he did, he no ſooner ſet ſight of the largeſt Glaſs, but he catches it, and drinks a good ſound draught of it, and ſo time after time, till he had taken all of them: and very much mending thereupon, ſent for another Pint more of the firſt he had ſent for, with this <hi>Commendum,</hi> That he hoped to ſee me ſuddenly: and was as good as his word.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing thus is their general per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance; helping and recovering in the extremities of thirſt, and moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Inflammations; notwithſtanding their manifeſt heat: It were but equal, all ſuch falſe-accuſing and unreaſonable Cautions ſhould for ever ceaſe, or be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more regarded, by whomſoever ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; and that whoever henceforth urges their familiar mildneſs, as a note of their Inſufficiency; (as our Mineral Practiſers uſe to do) when thus they have conſtantly manifeſted their power and efficacie in moſt dangerous caſes:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65062:31"/> may themſelves be noted of perverſeneſs in endeavouring to affright and dehort people, from their ſafeſt and moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Helpers, to a dependence on what is either inſufficient or hazardous.</p>
               <p>And truly ſome others, beſides the laſt mentioned, in their extremities have found ſtrength enough to break through theſe and the like cobweb-ſnares and ſcruples. One more eſpecially: who, after traverſing the uſual courſe of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick through and through; as purging, vomiting, bleeding, with Juleps upon Juleps, and Cordials upon Cordials of the beſt currant: and finding no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment or abatement of his moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent heat and thirſt; grew importunate for ſome of my Medicines, even to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience; which, though ſparingly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by his Phyſicians, and under uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al cautions for their heat; yet he took of them nevertheleſs freely and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; and upon a ſudden became ſo perfectly well, as was ſufficient to have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65062:32"/> converted a hundred Scruplers.</p>
               <p>And was not wholly fruitleſs: For, after this Gentleman walk'd abroad, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing often to viſit me, as one was treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with me about my Medicines for his Friend in a high Fever; upon taſting of them, objecting their Heat, as improper in ſuch caſes: This Gentleman noting it, ſays to him, <hi>Sir, let no body abuſe you with ſuch doubts; for I my ſelf being in as high a Fever, with extremity of thirſt and burning like the very fire, as I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve could not be exceeded; yet when all other means proved vain and ineffectual, theſe cool'd me, quench'd my thirſt, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me. But,</hi> ſays the other Gentleman, <hi>You took them then very warily, and in ſmall quantity:</hi> With that he catches a Glaſs which held about four ounces, ſays he, <hi>When I was at worſt, I drank thus much at a draught, and often.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, untill men of parts, art and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe enable themſelves better to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of Heats, and more accurately to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65062:32"/> diſcern of Virtues proper to Humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but continue perverſly to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, that becauſe this Medicine is as hot as Sack or White-wine, conclude it therefore as improper and dangerous to be adminiſter'd in ſickneſs; or, becauſe this or that Cordial Medicine is ſo mild, that people in health drink them as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly, as Burnt Claret or brew'd White-wine; therefore, alas, what power can ſuch have in Putrid Fevers, and Peſtilential Diſtempers: till they bluſh at ſuch unphiloſophical arguings, and ſearch deeper into the Myſtery of Heats and Mildneſs, and take in dayly ſome grains of Self-denyal, they will be apt either through partiality, to ſpeak worſe of things, than they know they do deſerve, or through error to ſpeak e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of things they know not: and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way are improper Guides, ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to miſlead the diſtreſſed in their greateſt extremities; and which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders this evident Teſt of Medicine of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65062:33"/> real and infinite uſe in ſuch doubtfull Judgings.</p>
               <p>But it fell out generally, if one ſaid I am dry already, and theſe will make me more thirſty; I am obſtructed, and theſe cannot but be binding; I ſweat, and theſe will certainly increaſe it; I am ſubject to be diſturb'd in my head, and theſe muſt needs intoxicate: It was great odds but ſome or other would ſoon aſſure the contrary from their own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. All which their benign qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and exemption from evil, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ow unto their coherence with the true Humane Complexion: a Conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, though abſolutely requiſite to the <hi>Art of Health,</hi> yet, I doubt, too great a ſtranger to be ſuddenly underſtood, or be bid welcom among Artiſts, ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally prepoſſeſſ'd; yet Time and a good <hi>Touchſtone</hi> may make even the ſtouteſt ſtoop to reaſon.</p>
               <p>My next Inſtance is, of an ingenious generous Gentleman, who by violent
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65062:33"/> exerciſe had ſo overſtrained his body, that he was not able to go without much pain; after ſome diſcourſe, I ſent him two pints of two ſeveral Medicines, the one being to be frequently taken, and the other by two ounces every night: and by thus uſing them, he perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the ſame Gentleman, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time after, being ſorely afflicted with the Toothach, having taken many Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines in vain, complaining to me of it, I told him, I thought he might be certain of help that night, by taking a ſmall quantity of one of my Cordial Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines: at which he ſmil'd, and ask'd me, How a Cordial could help the Toothach? I ſaid, By extinguiſhing the venom that cauſed it; and it was rather queſtionable, What a real Cordial Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine could not do. Nay then, ſays he, If you are ſo confident, pray let me have one. So I gave him onely two ounces of one I had good experience of,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65062:34"/> half to be taken that night at reſting time, a little warm'd in his hand; and the other part, if he needed it, after his firſt ſleep. The firſt cur'd him; but for more ſecurity, he took the reſt next night, and ſo was throughly well; nor have I ever found a more certain courſe in this painfull diſtemper, though nor always ſo ſuddenly; and then ſhould be longer continued, with abſtinence from Wine and all groſs Diet, which further all Cures.</p>
               <p>And ſince this performance; It hath not onely done this Gentlemnan the like ſervice; but when at any time he hath any ways been indiſpoſed, &amp; ſometimes he hath been ſo feveriſh, that he hath thought there was no way but by bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet even then two ounces of the ſame Medicine, or at moſt four ounces for twice taking, hath not failed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge all to his full ſatisfaction; plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo ſhewing, that a kindly true huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd Medicine, may be proper and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65062:34"/> in ſeveral Diſtempers.</p>
               <p>Another ſeeking my help, was a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman: Her Servant brings an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinal, deſired me to look on that Water; I told her it was not my way: She ask't me, how then I would underſtand the Diſeaſe? I ask't her, if ſhe knew any that could tell whether it proceeded as it was from Man, Woman or Child: She ſaid, ſhe could: I told her, in that ſhe knew more than any Phyſician could be ſure of, let him pretend what skill he would; and that unleſs ſhe had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe to ſay, I ſhould talk no longer with her: With that ſhe nam'd a very worthy perſon, and ſome of her Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, that ſhe had been long under Phyſick, but yet remained in extreme weakneſs. Many queſtions I ask'd her, which ſhe could not reſolve, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired I would give her a viſit: I told her, I did not uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o viſit any; but if ſhe pleas'd to ſend one to me that could ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint me expreſly with her condition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:65062:35"/> I would aſſiſt her the beſt I could.</p>
               <p>So next morning, her Siſter came to me. But inſtead of farther informing me how ſhe was, ſhe onely importun'd me to ſee her. I told her, I did not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd viſits, becauſe I was unwilling to attend any; but as not judging it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, my experience aſſuring me I could perform as much upon good informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as upon ſight. She ſeem'd to muſe at it, yet would have no denyal, but I muſt promiſe to ſee her without delay; which I performed: and truly ſhe was brought extreme low, look'd like death it ſelf, and even hopeleſs of recovery; giving me withall ſo clouded a counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as much diſlik'd me. But ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing me by her, ſhe related to me the original and progreſs of her Diſtemper, how long ſhe had been ill, what abundance of means ſhe had uſed, by adviſe of ſuch as ſhe knew both able and faithful; and yet nought availed, but that ſhe was as I ſaw her.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65062:35"/>
               <p>Upon which, I told her, I did believe there was yet other means and more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual than had been uſed: She ſaid, Every one ſpake well of their own, but ſhe found little comfort; asking me whether I ever ſaw any in her condition? I told her I had never ſeen two perſons in all reſpects diſtemper'd alike: She askt me whether I had ever cur'd any in her caſe, or like it? I ask't her, whether ſhe would not be well pleaſed to be the firſt? She ſaid, ſhe did not like to run any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards. I told her, if ſhe refer'd herſelf to me, ſhe ſhould run none at all; for what I intended to give her, ſhe ſhould, if ſhe pleaſed, ſee me or any in our houſe take the like quantity of the ſame before her. She ſaid, that was fair; but then how could things ſo familiar, work ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a maſs of rooted corruption, as ſhe was loaded with in every part of her. I told her, I did not doubt of it, and that ſhe ſhould find all her diſtempers inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly vaniſh; and that by ſuch pleaſing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65062:36"/> means, as ſhe would never be unwilling to take. With that ſhe ſmil'd, and wiſht ſhe could believe it. I told her, there lay all the difficulty; becauſe as to that point, how far my words were to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, I ſhould be ſilent; ſhe muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of that ſome other way, and ought to have been done before I was ſent for: and with that was taking my leave. But ſhe ſtayd me with a Glaſs of Wine, and offer'd me money; which I refuſed, being unwilling to be ſo inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. So ſhe wiſht me to prepare what I thought needfull for her that night, and ſhe would ſend for it, and in the morning I ſhould hear how ſhe was, and would take what I ſent her, and obſerve my counſel ſolely.</p>
               <p>Which ſhe did moſt exactly, though there wanted not who would have been buſie with their gentle Purgers, as they ſomewhat undeſervedly intitle their Looſners; which uſually cleanſe but as dirty beeſoms, that too often make a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65062:36"/> worſe kind of filth than they avoyd, and more dangerous, even to the defilement of the Bloud and Spirits. But as hap was, I had her promiſe againſt all inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medlings; and in little more than a weeks time made all my words ſo good, (and that ſolely by Medicines agreeable to this Teſt) that ſhe went immediately and chearfully into the countrey, taking for her <hi>Viaticum,</hi> a good quantity of a Cordial fit for the occaſion.</p>
               <p>And the circumſtances of this, and many of the other inſtances warily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; as on the one hand they manifeſt that generally it is far more difficult to perſuade Patients of the poſſibility of their cure, than to cure them: ſo alſo, how apt they are both to give large cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, where they have cauſe enough of ſcruple, (as in the common road of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick) and to diſtruſt where there is no cauſe of fear at all; and this for want of ſome certain marks of diſtinction upon Medicines whereby to guide their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65062:37"/> which poſſibly this, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Touchſtone</hi> may henceforth happily ſupply.</p>
               <p>Beſides, in all my Obſervation of her confuſed complicated Diſtempers; I could aſcribe them to nothing more, than to the variety and frequency of purgative and vomitive Medicines, ſhe had long time been accuſtomed to; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving ſuch Diſtempers impoſſible to be otherwiſe removed: yea ſo bewitched are moſt people therewith, that they never think or ſpeak of Phyſick or Medicine, but they intend Vomiters o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Looſners, as if nothing elſe deſerv'd the name of Phyſick, but ſuch as brought them pain or torture; frequently left them in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or prepared for future miſchief: as this Gentlewoman ſadly found to her coſt. But it's hopeful, time and a little conſideration will produce a better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in matters of ſo great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Whilſt this Cure was in agitation: a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65062:37"/> Child in the countrey, very dear and nearly related to them, being extremely ill, my help was deſired; I ſent onely three ounces of one of my Medicines, by which it recovered.</p>
               <p>Many other particulars, worthy note, have been ſince performed by the like Medicines, for this worthy Family and their alliance, divers large quantities being frequently fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cht for their occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to their their contentful ſatisfaction: plainly ſhewing how much may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, where there are ſtore of ſuch real Medicines, without the nic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, pulſes, and ſuch predictive curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, which too often diſtract both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients and Phyſicians, or but rarely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them to any material indication.</p>
               <p>Another Lady<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſome miles from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> in a moſt terrible Fever, and after long proceeds in the beſt of uſual Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, farther to ſeek, and more threatned with the ſaddeſt iſſue; being perſuaded by a friend, ſent for ſome of my Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65062:38"/> by allowance of her Doctors. I ſent her ſix ounces of one moſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate; and ſending again, I ſent as much of another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and next time, of the firſt the like quantity; by help of which ſhe perfectly recovered, with very thankfull reſpects to her Phyſicians, for their ſo ſignal freedom and ſelf-denyal in her preſervation.</p>
               <p>About this time I received a Letter from a young Gentleman, a ſtranger to me, concluding I could certainly cure him of many diſtempers therein related, chiefly a violent pain in his Head and Breaſt, which had coſt him much in Phyſick without any benefit. I ſent him a Pinte mixt and made up of two of my Medicines, adviſing him to take it in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts at four nights, which he did; and immediately after came with a great deal of joy, telling me he was perfectly well: and which occaſion'd many of his friends and relations, people of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to apply themſelves to the uſe of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65062:38"/> theſe Medicines for ſundry infirmities, ſpeeding no worſe than he had done: and ſome of them receiving that ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from them, which they could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe within the power of Art to have effected.</p>
               <p>Which I thus expreſs, to ſhew that it is no abſurdity, even for Perſons of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to put ſo much truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in ſome Students or Arts-men; as to take freely and without ſcruple thoſe preparations, which they judg requiſite for their recovery, though they know no part of their Ingredients, as theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy perſons moſt readily did; deeming it no diſparagement at all to be governed in ſuch caſes, wholly by an implicite Faith, as ſome cenſoriouſly term all truſts of this nature; whoſe overmuch warineſs is generally puniſhed with falſe ſtories of what is given them, or with ſupplies onely of vulgar inſignificant Medicines, and ſo by being over care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, too frequently trifle away their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65062:39"/> lives and money: for an Arts-man ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting by his Art, being owner of it no longer than he keeps it to himſelf, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more improper or unwelcom than to ask diſcovering Queſtions; nor would it need at all, where ſuch a Teſt as this once comes to bear rule amongſt the Noble or ingenious, becauſe upon tryal every one would and might freely truſt as he had occaſion.</p>
               <p>Another young Gentleman was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to my care, who had wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelf out with ſeeking remedy for a long ſettled pain within the uppermoſt part of his breaſt, and ſharp painfull Rheums in his head, with a cough, and an Hectick Fever. The firſt I gave him was onely four ounces of ſo fortunate a Medicine, for two nights, as quite took away the pain of his breaſt; after which applying himſelf to ſome others of them his Conſtitution became ſo renewed and fixed, that I believe in maintenance of their innocencie and efficacie, he would
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65062:39"/> not fear to enter the Liſts with the moſt captious or capricious Artiſt; nor in the moſt contageous Time or moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Diſtemper, would be drawn to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on any other, either Preſervatives or Remedies.</p>
               <p>Another inſtance is of a Gentleman of worth and judgment; whoſe Lady, newly delivered, and her child dying, fell into a feveriſh ſadneſs. He wrote to me her condition, with this alſo, that he knew nothing ſo fit for her, as ſome of my Medicines, deſiring I would ſend ſuch as I thought good: ſo I ſent one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly four ounces of the moſt appropriate, which ſhe took, and after that, ſent for the like quantity of the ſame, and once more for the like alſo, with which ſhe became perfectly well; and if this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der caſe do not ſufficiently prove their heat to be innocent, and their mildneſs to be accompanied with power, it muſt be ſure with thoſe with whom reaſon is of no validity.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:65062:40"/>
               <p>One whoſe children had often been recovered by my Medicines, came haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon me from a friend of his, whoſe young Daughter of about Fourteen, was as he ſaid, in a very hopeleſs condition, earneſtly deſiring me to go and ſee her. I askt him, how long ſhe had been ill? He told me, a long time, and the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and means uſed, but all in vain. I told him, I had declined the uſual way of practiſe, and viſited none, nor was willing to meddle where others had the care. He ſaid, her father had lately bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried two very hopeful children, and ſo much feared this, that he was reſolved ſhe ſhould take no more of them; and ſo much importun'd me, that I went with him; finding her quite waſted and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt breathleſs, and in a very high fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; I ſpake chearfully to her, &amp; raiſed ſome hopes in her and her ſad friends, wiſhing them to ſend to me within two hours: So I ſent her three ounces of an appropriate pleaſant Medicine to take
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65062:40"/> two ſpoonfulls every three hours, and to ſend for more when it was ſpent. She took it with delight, and ſo with the uſe onely of this, continued for about Eight days, ſhe went well abroad, and kept within no more through any infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
               <p>One whoſe child I had formerly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, paſſing by, ſeemed full of care, and being gone a little, returned ſuddenly, and told me her child that I once recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, was dangerouſly ill, and that ſhe had been with a Phyſician, an old friend of hers, who ordered her to be bled, and ask't what I thought of it; I told her, 'twas improper for me to meddle in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others buſineſs, yet that it would be fit before the child was bled, being not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove five years old, to adviſe with ſome others; and ask't her, if he had directed any thing elſe? with that ſhe ſhewed a Glaſs with about three ounces of a very ordinary weak Julep, which after I had taſted, I gave to a Gentlemen of skill and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65062:41"/> learning, deſiring his judgment of it in ſo dangerous a fever: and he ſaying it was very mean, ſhe ask'd me if I could give her any thing more effectual, and ſpare her bleeding; I ſaid, I thought I could; and filling a Glaſs of about two ounces, gave to her and the Gentleman to taſt; and he ſaying it was full of life, ſhe haſted away with it, and gave it to the child, by which ſhe recovered per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly without bleeding; which may poſſibly excuſe this irregularity.</p>
               <p>Another inſtance is of a young Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, ſomewhat conſumptive, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly troubled with continual pains in his head, who after long toyling under Phyſick, deſired my advice, but withall ſaid, he was inclined to the uſe of that a Friend of his had received much good by, and it being very proper for him, he took with him a large quantity, and lives very comfortably in the frequent uſe of it, reſolving where ere he is, not to be without it, or ſome other of its neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-Medicines.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:65062:41"/>
               <p>Another young Gentleman, who had contracted a very ill habit of body, by being ſo ſurpriz'd with Snow in the night, that he was almoſt frozen to death; yet in time ſomewhat growing it out, ſettled in <hi>London.</hi> Where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained very uncomfortably, full of pains and weakneſs, which he endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to remove by all the means of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick he poſſibly could imagine, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of prevailing, growing worſe and worſe, he came to me, deſiring my help whatever it ſhould coſt. He had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual pains in his head, with want of ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, ſoreneſs all over his body, a moſt heavy dullneſs and indiſpoſition to his occaſions, took joy in nothing, as was too eaſily diſcernable by the ſad aſpect of an ingenuous countenance. I gave him a Pint of a very general Medicine, which he was to take by little and little in a weeks time, holding it always a good while in his mouth before he ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it; which he carefully obſerved,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65062:42"/> and fetcht another Pint; and ſo by three or four Pints became perfectly well; &amp; occaſioned divers of his friends to make uſe both of this and others: and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon ſudden illneſs made uſe of them himſelf, to his conſtant ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>Another inſtance of their benign qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, agreeing with this Teſt, is of one near Fifty, who very much pleaſing him ſelf on all occaſions with ſmall Mineral Pills, mightily cry'd up for all manner of virtues: upon an extreme Cold ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken falling into a Surfet, with a violent Fever, vehement thirſt, and tedious fits; adviſed with the Author of thoſe Pills, who ordered him to take a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, which working both ways with him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet worſe upon it; ſent again, and was ordered more; but being ſtill worſe, he ſent again, and was ſtill ordered to take more; which he not liking to do, ſent his Wife to me, his condition then being very dangerous:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65062:42"/> who relating to me all I have expreſt, I told her, He who firſt had him in hand, ought to amend his errour; and that it could not ſeem meet for any other to meddle; none knowing ſo wel as he, what he had given; and that if things never ſo ſafe ſhould be preſcribed, and the event ſucceeded not to his recovery, the blame might be laid nevertheleſs upon it; and ſo adviſed her to return to him: She ſaid, He would give no other but thoſe Pills, and ſhe was ſure her Husband would take no more of them; earneſtly deſiring me to ſend him ſomewhat. I told her, I would ſend him nothing but what ſhould be as ſafe as breaſt-milk for children; but it ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld be ſhe, and not I, that ſhould undergo the iſſue. So I gave her a Pint of an appropriate Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, which he took by two, three and four ounces at a time: and ſo with the uſe of two Pints more, perfectly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, thankfully acknowledging its wonderfull effects, eſpecially in quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65062:43"/> his thirſt, which he thought impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; by a Medicine ſo apparently hot: But ſayes he I perceive now it is but an abuſe to bid beware of their Heat (ſome or other having been buſie with their cautions) for it coold me and quencht my thirſt, and extinguiſh my Feaver, in the moſt contentfull manner imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>Another Inſtance, Is of a Gentleman of middle age, who upon Heats and Colds, much intention of buſineſs and neglect of uſual Dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, fell into an irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome frequent provocation to Stool; but with utmoſt ſtriving voyded no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, deſiring my adviſe I gave him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver night three ounces of a General Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine; for which next day he gave me hearty thanks, his body then working naturally and ſufficiently: Though this Medicine, I believe was never exceeded in ſtaying of Looſneſſes, which ſhews it to be of the true Humane ſtrain and virtue.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:65062:43"/>
               <p>The ſame Gentleman long before this upon every Cold taken falling into a dangerous Quinſie, and ſtil thereupon bled in the Tongue and in the Arm; with the general courſe of Phyſick uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in ſuch caſes: and every time more and more threatning; I at length told him this way could not but ſo impair his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that at length it would fail him and leav him in the lurch when he ſtood moſt in need of help, &amp; withal that by a good and real Medicine this flattering way of bleeding might be prevented: So next time he took my counſil, and by four ounces of an appropriate Medicince ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for two nights; it diſcharged the Quinſie and prevented bleeding and all other inconveniences, and was never ſince troubled after that manner.</p>
               <p>The ſame perſon at another time, ſo Heart-ſick and Feaveriſh, that he thought it impoſſible to eſcape a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous fit of Sickneſs: by one three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Generall Medicine, inſtantly and perfectly recovered.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:65062:44"/>
               <p>Alſo this Gentlemans Wife ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had many fits of Sickneſſes, and ſome very threatning and dangerous; beſides her Breeding times, times of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor and Lyings In, depending general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon theſe Medicines never failed of her deſired help: nor ever uſed other as upon importunity, ſometime ſhe hath done, but ſhe repented it; as ſhe hath often ſadly acknowledged: Being now fixed to their uſe paſt all removing; her Children have often recovered alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers dangerous diſtempers and fits of Sickneſſes: And her Mother although far in years and ful of infirmities, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned originally from unhappy advice to bleed in her youth; and alſo by preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mineral Vomits, yet by the conſtant uſe of theſe, though in ſomwhat ſcanty quantities, hath been preſerved beyond all expectation, maintaining a pregnancy and cheerfulneſs hardly to be found in younger and ſtronger people; ſo exceedingly doe they oppoſe the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes of Age and Sickneſs.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:65062:44"/>
               <p>Another inſtance, Is of a young Gentlewoman, who after a long journey into the Country and different Diet, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her return to London, upon drinking Milk and over eating Summer Fruit took a Surfit with an high Fever, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with vomiting, ſoreneſs of Throat, tedious empty coughing, which brought her ſo extream low, as was thought impoſſible for her to eſcape; yet continually taking plentifully of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of theſe Medicines, and no other (though much urged) ſhe at length be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all hope recovered.</p>
               <p>Which plenteous taking is the more to be noted; becauſe therein, in difficult Caſes, chiefly reſts the efficacy, and without which people do but Flatrer themſelves with vain hopes of wonders from ſmal matters and little charges; a humor which hath coſt many there pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and too many their lives, to be rid of painfull dangerous diſtempers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by their boldneſs with cheap
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65062:45"/> Phyſick, which ever and anon are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded upon the over eaſie and credulous who rather then their lives would faine be cured by miracle, that is for nothing.</p>
               <p>Beſides I have obſerved ſome groſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, theſe reall Medicines have ſuffered by the crafty unfairneſs of ſome practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, who when after long endevours in their uſuall way of purging, vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting bleeding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And their Patients as quite tired growing importunate for ſome of my Medicines, they have uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given way for a ſmal quantity; and then nothing the ſmal effects of things ſo much talkt of, turn to their patients and relations, telling them they may ſee they are but as other things, ſometimes prevailing and ſometimes no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and ſo at once diſparaging the Medicines, and clear their readines to allow of any thing for their recovery: an unbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubtilty I found more frequently than is imaginable, and from ſome, who carry it very ſmoothly: of which one
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65062:45"/> inſtance may be needfull.</p>
               <p>Being cal'd in all haſte to ſpeak with one, A maid attending told me her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs who lay very ill deſired ſomething to ſtay her vomiting, for ſhe could not retain any thing ſhe took, I askt where ſhe dwelt, and perceived her to be one, who had been well acquainted with my way, a young daughter of hers having been cured by my Medicines: I askt what Phyſitians ſhe had, and divers were named, I askt whether ſhe came with their allowance, ſhe ſaid ſhe did, at which, as I wondred, ſo I apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all hope was over, and ſcrupled ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any; but the maid would have no denial; ſo although I ſaw it would be to no purpoſe but to undervalue my Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, yet out of my reſpects to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and their want ſhould not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to obſtinacy in me, I ſent two ounces of a Medicine, that taken in due time had ſtayed many ſuch diſtempers, adviſing more ſhould be ſent for as there
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:65062:46"/> was occaſion: But as I feared it was but a little time after that I ſaw all her rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Black.</p>
               <p>All which I have thus particularly expreſt, That henceforth it may be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly minded, how abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it is, upon every occaſion their aid is deemed requiſite not to defer their uſe too long, nor to give over too ſoon, nor to ſcruple to take them in full quantity; and in ſo doing none need to doubt a comfortable iſſue: nor are the ingenious to blame me if hereafter I withſtand all ſuch inſignificant tamperings, poſſibly to palliate the miſchievous error of a Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, with which the warieſt are frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too bold, to the irrevocable detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of bewailing patients and ther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</p>
               <p>My next inſtance of their innocency &amp; efficacy, Is of a young Gentlewoman, halfe gone of her firſt Childe, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a while in the Country, under far different accommodations than what her
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65062:46"/> abode in the City plentifully afforded, with ſome unuſual ſtirring in buſineſs, ſoon after her return, fell into a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Fever, with vomiting, bleeding at Noſtril, ſtartings and extream pains in her back: her husband finding the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper violent and threatning, adviſed with her Friends, and ſent for ſuch Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians as they liked, who for divers weeks dayly viſited, and adminiſtred to her with all poſſible care and tenderneſs even till every of them were hopeleſs of her recovery; her diſtempers not only proving obſtinate againſt all means they could imagine, there being no ſpare of coſt; but ran hourly into higher degrees of danger, upon which her husband la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting her condition to me, I told him I feared he would find her diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per far above the reach and controul of the uſual Phyſick, which he at length found too true, in that after all they could doe, her inflammation heightned into diſtraction &amp; perpetual reſtleſneſs,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65062:47"/> took nothing but vomited as ſoon as taken, painfull and tedious fits every night, waſted to a very Skelli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, meer skin and bone, nay ſo ruffe and ſhrivel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as ſeemed more like Fagot-ſticks, &amp; under intollerable thirſt; So as nothing but inevitable Death was hourly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, in this her wofull plight her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band full of griefe and fear deſires my aſſiſtance, I told him ſo long as there was life there was ſome hope, and that poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly there might be yet means for help, whereto I ſhould be moſt ready were it not that ſhe was in others hands, he ſaid all was at an end, &amp; none could blame ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him or me juſtly, however he would bear it all, earneſtly preſſing me to do my utmoſt: whereupon I gave him ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what above two ounces of a general Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, which that very night gave cauſe of hope, and ſo plying her both day and night with variety, and large quantities of theſe real Medicines for a long time by degrees her fits abated her thirſt cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65062:47"/> her reſt and appetite returned, her vomiting left; and after a while her fleſh and ſtrength was reſtored to a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: and in concluſion moſt happily and perfectly recovered, her Childe alſo born alive and without blemiſh, to the abaſhment of divers her Friends and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitants; who uſually threatned ſhe would undoe her ſelf by ſuch hot Medicines, and bring a raw and ſcalded Childe into the world: but indeed how could they well do leſs hearing continually as they do the wary cautions of the learned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the uſe of hot things in ſuch caſes but ſure there are hopes, ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as are here plentifully diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red will in time incline them better to diſtinguiſh of Heats; for during the whole time of her taking them, there was not the leaſt ill effect to be charged upon; them though upon ſome acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal relapſes ſhe took in a ſhort ſpace a pint and a halfe of one of them: every bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of nature alſo being conſtantly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65062:48"/> and injoyed as freely and orderly as could be wiſhed: So that both ſhe and her husband recived ſo great an aſſurance of their innocency notwithſtanding their hear, and of their efficacy and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, for all their mildneſs &amp; pleaſantneſs That under God, they have both for themſelves, their children and Family, ſolely depended on them ever ſince, are never without good quantities of them alwayes in readineſs: and have time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time told me ſo many remarkable ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of their happy performances, that were I torecite them; in likelyhood they equall halfe my Inſtances which ſhewes how proper and beneficial this kinde of Phyſick would prove for Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</p>
               <p>Nor did he deem them deer (which ſome having nothing elſe to ſay, are wont to object to withhold and reſtrain their uſe) his firſt courſe of Phyſick un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which ſhe was not recovered, coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him three times more than this that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:65062:48"/> reſtored her to her health.</p>
               <p>But if this ſeems not cheap enough, what will they ſay to this which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; for one who was very ſenſible of this cure and the means thereof a while after falling into a moſt violent Feaver, and into the hands of the moſt eminent Phyſitians; who yet doing all they could prevailed nothing: and he in his extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities calling often for ſome of my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, either not underſtood or not heeded: at length when every one thought him paſt all hope, and in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſive ſtrugglings of Death; as himſelf after told me, thoſe very motions; which thoſe who ſtood by him deemed no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but the immediate preface to his Death proceeded ſolely from a ſtrong perſwaſion in his Dream, that he was drinking full quantities of my Medicines for they told him that he often cagerly lifted both his hands up to his mouth, and down again; and ſo up and down til he fell faſt aſleep, and waked in a well
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65062:49"/> compoſed condition, which hourly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to his compleat recovery: and I think he owes my Studies at leaſt a great good turn for it: or who will not ſay this Cure was too too cheap in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>My next Inſtance is, of a Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who upon many occaſions of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper had continually found help by my Medicines; but being neer to other Aſſiſtance and much out of order; took ſomething that brought ſuch unuſuall pains and ſhootings about her, that ſhe knew not what to think of her ſelf, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed very like to the occult remains of Mineral Medicines: and ſoon after fell into a violent Looſneſs with extreme Gripings: So upon a ſudden I was ſent to, and I ſent her a quarter of a pint of an appropriate Medicine not uſed to fail in ſuch Caſes, which being all taken a little warm, perfectly recovered her.</p>
               <p>But the laſt cure ended not ſo; for within two dayes after, the Husband of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65062:49"/> that Gentlewoman came haſtily to me, ſadly lamenting an elderly Friend of his who lay in a very hopeleſs condition, by occaſion only of a Cold at firſt, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fit and Fever, which under his Phyſitians hands increaſed upon him and being bound in his body, they gave him various looſning or purging Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines: but yet do what they could nothing prevailed, but ſet him into extreme vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miting, which what with the fears of his Phyſitians and his own, very much aggravated his miſery: They excuſing the not working of their Looſners, by a Rupture the Patient had had for twelve yeers, ſaying, his Gutts were twiſted, and rendered it impoſſible to move his body downward; ſo ſtrongly conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt are they in uncertainties notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their exact curiotſiy in Anotamy, in Circulation, Sanguification, Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hilification; by which they would ſeem to take their aim ſo right as not to miſs a Hairs breadth of a Diſeaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50-110" type="pages">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:65062:50"/>
               <p>I told him, he might too eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive there was ſmal hope of life; and the rather, becauſe he was loaded with ſo many Laxative Medicines, which confounded nature and occaſioned thoſe perpetual provocations to Vomiting; but that withall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I did not believe his Guts were twiſted; or that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to move his Body downward, if it were fairly attempted by ſome kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and powerfull friend to Nature, not looſning; but ſuch as by its benign quality would perform what the Body moſt needed: He ſaid it ſeemed ſtrange the Body in ſuch a Caſe ſhould be mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed downward without a purging Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, being ſo extremely obſtructed as his was: yet what I thought fit, he knew he could perſwade him to take: I told him, that he might plainly diſcern the truth of what I ſaid (there being indeed nothing more proper) I would ſend him the very ſame Medicine to looſen his friends body, which I had given to his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65062:50"/> Wife to ſtay her looſneſſe, and which he knew had cured her: So he took with him halfe a pint of the ſame, to be given by four ſpoonfulls every hour, till it was ſpent: after the third taking he Vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a little; and after the fourth his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy workt downward very effectually, which put him into ſo much hope, that he reſted wel that night: But next day altered again, more I believe through the venomous nature of the Laxatives by which his Spirits were perplext and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, than through the diſtemper it ſelf; Beſides he was far in years and weakned by his rupture: yet nezt evening he ſent for half a pint more of the ſame: But liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to take any or very little of it: yet was exceeding thankful to his Friend for performing ſo much as he did for him, ſeeming to believe the ſame means ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in time, was likely to have cured him: And though it did not; yet may well ſtand as a real Medicine: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this <hi>Touchſtone,</hi> in its main and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65062:51"/> moſt probationary Character.</p>
               <p>Nor did this thus end neither; For this Sick mans Sonnes Wife a young Gentlewoman in the Houſe; having been long ill with a continual Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Sickneſſe at Stomack; obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the kindly operation of this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, reſolved to take the remainder her ſelf: and by degrees took all; but blam'd her ſelf exceedingly ſoon after; becauſe for about a weeks time, ſhe frequently vomitted, and feared ſhe ſhould be worſe upon it: but her fear proved all her harm her vomitting not only ſoon ceaſing; but all her other pains and ſickneſſes, with much joy and thanks to her friend who made her acquainted with it: And this effect I think, if any thing were wanting compleats the Character: and ſhewes alſo, how beneficiall it is to uſe Medicines of ſo general and ſafe a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that never decay, nor ſo much as a ſpoonfull over-caſe away.</p>
               <p>Another Inſtance is, Of a Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65062:51"/> who being with one that for ſome ſpice of Scurvy and Dropſie, was taking a Vomit; ſhe alſo upon ſmal perſwaſion took the ſame quantity; which ſo altered the ſtate of her Stomack, that long time after ſhe was frequently moleſted with extream pains &amp; ſickneſs; which coſt her ſome Doſes of my Medicines by ſtarts for caſe; but not followed: but one fit at laſt ſhe had above the reſt, that ſhe thought a Preface to her Death; yet ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon four ounces of Appropriate Medicine in leſſe than a quarter of an hours time perfectly cured her: which with the many other benefits ſhe receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from my Medicines, before and ſince in the Sickneſſe time; and other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hath wrought ſo effectually upon her eſtimation, that ſhe perſwades all her friends and acquaintance to depend ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon them.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman in an high Fever, and violent tooth-ake; taking two ounces of an appropriate Medicine, in one night
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65062:52"/> it drive out a large ſwelling under his Ear: which next night upon the like quantity of another, was very much aſſwaged, and next night after the like quantity of a third, quite diſcharged and perfectly cured him.</p>
               <p>A middle aged man taken ſuddenly with pains, and giddineſſe like as the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Peſtilence, taking inſtantly four ounces of an appropriate Medicine; immediately recovered.</p>
               <p>Another ſmitten into a moſt violent Feaver withall imaginable ſigns of the Sickneſs: yet plyed continually day and night with variety and large quantities of theſe Medicines, recovered without any ſwelling.</p>
               <p>Another extreamly penſive with thought of the Sickneſs, and haſting out of town: feeling many ſigns of its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch, taking with him good quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of theſe Medicines and uſing of them plentifully, eſcaped the Infection.</p>
               <p>And the ſame Gentleman ſince; upon
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65062:52"/> ſuch violent fits of diſtemper: as he thought could not poſſibly end, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with death, ſickneſs and tedious courſe of Phyſick; yet through Gods goodneſs hath never failed of help and recovery ſomtimes by one, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by variety of theſe Medicines: and which he acknowledgeth to have done him ſingular ſervice in his journies and at the Bath; where for want of ſuch kindly helpers, depending upon what<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> improper: Its to be feared many fail to the diſhonor of thoſe excellent Waters.</p>
               <p>Another inſtance is of a Gentleman, who recovering his loſt Appetite, by the frequent uſe of divers of my Medicines; having been long troubled with the Gout, which generally afflicting him in a part of his foot, was now flown into the upper back part of his ſhoulder, with ſuch painfulneſs as was intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I perſwaded him to take a full quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, or doſe of an appropriate Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, being neer upon four ounces,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:65062:53"/> which ſuddenly ſickned him extreamly, and inclined him to lye down upon a bed, where inſtantly he fell into a ſound ſleep for at leaſt two hours: and wak'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heartily well and cheerful free from all touch of pain or ſickneſs: And this from no ſleepy or ſtupifying quality in the Medicine; for I as carefully ſhun all enforcers of reſt; by <hi>Opium</hi> under any form, or under any correction, as I doe the uſe of Minerals; as weakners of the Nerves and diſtroyers of the animal Spirits.</p>
               <p>Another Inſtance is, Of one who ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complained he was ſore all over his body, hardly able to ſtir, giddy headed, had no appetite, but ſuch a naſty taſte up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his pallate, and in his ſtomack as was extream loathſome: It was not a time of Peſtilence, though theſe ſigns ſignified little leſſe: I asked him what he uſed to doe when he was ſick, he ſaid his wife uſed to make him a <hi>Carduus</hi> Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, I bid him get one inſtantly and drink
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:65062:53"/> well of it: but an hour after bethinking my ſelf how dangerouſly ill he was, and that if that night were trifled away, all help might come too late, I went to him and found him ſitting by his fire very ſadly; having taken nothing nor any thing providing for him: ſo I gave him about three ounces of an appropriate Medicine, with which he reſted well all that night: and next morning ſtanding at his dore I askt him how twas with him, he ſaid never better; but that he had now a great ſwelling behind his ear; I was glad I had done as I did: he would have had ſomewhat to ripen it, but I would not, and it went down of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Another being extream ill, wholly neglected all means; but at length deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me to give him ſomthing, which I did: but being not preſently well, grew humorous and would take nothing but cold water; by which he brought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into a moſt violent Fever, with thirſt, flegm, vomitting, and reſtleſneſs,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:65062:54"/> and ſoon after ſo wild, as he was fain to be held in his bed: all which time I cauſed thoſe about him to ply him day and night, with plenty and divers of my Medicines, which yet prevailed ſo ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: that ſomewhat elſe was preſcribed him by one who ſaid he had all the ſigns of death upon him: but twas not given him, ſo for one whole night he had no reliefe by Medicine at all: which I no ſooner heard, but I preſently ſent him ſuch as were proper; as deeming it unreaſonable to deſiſt ſo long as there is life, having found it alwaies good, ſtill to hope the beſt, and to uſe the utmoſt means<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by which divers have recovered that were thought impoſſible; as this almoſt dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man did, to the wonder of all his friends, who during his cure, were much troubled becauſe of his long co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiveneſſe; but I quicted them, by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the danger of moving his body till the venome of the diſeaſe was wholly ſubdued, and that in due time they
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:65062:54"/> would ſee nature ſo enabled by theſe Medicines as freely and without force it would perform that and all other needfull offices; which came to paſſe to their full ſatisfaction: but had he been attended (as too many) with ſuch as will be asking continually, what do ye think of him; if you think he cannot eſcape, pray deal plainly, that we may not ſpend more money to no purpoſe; a courſe as deſtructive as vile and hatefull: and had it been ſo here, he had certainly dyed for it; for there was no hope but in a conſtant perſeverance.</p>
               <p>And now I think it cannot with any colour of reaſon be denied, but that the Inſtances recited, do fully amount in their performances to what is afore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be the proper effects of real Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, and in every reſpect to anſwer thoſe Characters, which I have here e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed for a Standard, Teſt or <hi>Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> to try and prove, whether Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are ſuch or not, as may rationally
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:65062:55"/> be relyed on in caſes of extremity: and may as I conceive ſuffice to witneſs, both the ſubſtantiality of thoſe Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, and that there are ſuch Medicines really in being: Teſtifying alſo that my conceptions of Mans true Original and of his true Complexion: unto which I have bowed all my Studies &amp; Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have in no wiſe miſled me; but ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually governed and ſteered my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors as to render them far beyond the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual ſucceſs of firſt diſcoverers; and much more true, uſefull and certain than other Phyſiology.</p>
               <p>And as to their extent in Cure, I have frequently and impartially compared the real Virtues and properties of theſe real Medicines, with all the curable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes (the Foul excepted, with which I never meddle) mentioned in the largeſt Bills of Mortallity, with Captain <hi>Grants</hi> ingenious Comment thereupon: I have conſidered ſeriouſly of them in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: and upon the whole can ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:65062:55"/> to doubt; but that taken in time with due perſeverance in their uſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for prevention or for cure; they are likely to prove far more pertinent, ſafe and effectual, than any Helpers, Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatives or Medicines; all their marks and performances conſidered, than ever yet were tendered to human aſſiſtance; and this even in the Peſtilence it ſelfe, for though I ſtaid not in <hi>London</hi> paſt the increaſe of two Thouſand a Week; but was forced away or muſt be cruel where all obligations of tenderneſs lay upon me: yet took I care tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nothing of mine ſhould be wanting to any, who deſired to make uſe of them; with ſome liberty of freely helping the neceſſitous: beſides I had long declined Practice, viſited none, nor had then ſo much as one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient under my Hand: and withall had ſo publiſhed the Vertues and Uſes of all my Medicines; as ſufficed both to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and to inſtruct every one ſo plainly, as without further direction or
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:65062:56"/> attendance, every one might be in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of helping themſelves and their relations upon any occaſion: for ſo I judged it moſt proper, both for the good of Patients and Phyſitians; and poſſibly would ſoon ſo appear to Magiſtrates al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in ſuch Infectious and dangerous times, were they accuſtomed to note the happy union of Safety and Power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned in one and the ſame Medicine: or would ſtrictly hold Phyſitians and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſers to ſuch Marks and Characters of real Medicines, as would witneſs them to be ſuch as might juſtly be depended on in that violent diſtemper: becauſe being ſuch all people might without danger confidently and freely make uſe of them in all ſtates and degrees of the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, without any attendance or danger to Phyſitians; it being true and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Medicines, that is ſolely to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in all contagious Diſtempers: And it was no ſmal quantity, I provided for the occaſion, from my obſervation of a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:65062:56"/> general taint in Nature for ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time before; ſo there was no want of what I could furniſh; at leaſt for a ſeaſon,</p>
               <p>But yet, though I had great aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, both of the propriety and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of my Preſervatives and Remedies, as whoever well weigh the inſtances precedent, may well believe I had good cauſe: yet obſerving how from all quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Medicines were loudly voiced out, as moſt certain in the caſe.—I could not at any hand bring my mind to any freſh publication, leaſt I might poſſibly draw people from what was more, to what was leſs effectual, for more could not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt for prevalence, then was of every of them; how they anſwered it in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance: after I had taſted and noted divers of them, I ſoon ſaw cauſe to greive and fear, ſeeing ſo weak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion againſt ſo powerful an Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
               <p>Beſides to publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh then a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſh, when
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:65062:57"/> in reaſon I done enough before, and was dayly to be ſeen; ſeemed ſo like raiſing a new Mart for ſale, for trade, and mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as became not the ſadneſs of the Seaſon, requiring rather a giving than a receiving hand, and wherein very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to their eternal praiſe abounded.</p>
               <p>But although the help I left proved more faithful, then skilful, diſpoſing of much, and taking but little accompt of the ſucceſs; yet it amounts to thus much that divers under God imputed their exemption from the Infection unto them: and divers their cure wholly to their uſe without farther help or atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance: and this too in as dangerous a ſtate of the diſeaſe as could poſſibly be; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>okens only excepted, in which I doe not know they were ever proved, though I am not wholly without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, even in that diſmal caſe, were they taken in large quantity.</p>
               <p>And I have ſomewhat wondered that one, who practiced much with them
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:65062:57"/> long before; and from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ending of that ſad Mortalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that was viſited; ſometimes by fifty in a morning, and viſited the ſick all day after, and moſt part of the night; and reckons never were any Medicines like them for certainty, that at thrice taking of them, they never failed of cure, in ſo much as they ſeemed almoſt mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, and upon their taſte, were highly approved by the Maſter of the Peſt-houſe; yet gives he no account of any attempt made by him upon the Tokens, unleſs upon a woman, whom he ſaies, being ſpeechleſs, and her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band urging him to procure him but a few words from her; by a quantity forced upon her, he ſo far prevailed, that ſhe did ſpeak to him to his ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but no more: And this being true, what timely taken, and continued at d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> diſtance in full quantity, gives much cauſe of hope; but I heartily wiſh there may never more be ſuch occaſion.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:65062:58"/>
               <p>But for their effecacy in preſerving from the infection, or expelling the vennom as ſoon as taken, and their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valence in cure; I ſhall give for each an inſtance.</p>
               <p>And the firſt, pleaſe to take in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs of a Letter from <hi>London,</hi> from one who returning thither, had furniſhed himſelf with divers of my Medicines, as fearing the worſt; and at the place of my abode, thus ſaluted me. Sir, Next to Divine goodneſs, I deem my ſelf bound to return you my hearty thanks for my preſent health, which had been much indangered but for your C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdials; for what through change of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, Diet and Lodging, with ſome what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> then uſual b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſelling in buſineſs, I found my ſelfe much out of tune, but could not ſay I was ill until the laſt Tueſday night: but then after the whole daies Indiſpoſition, I was taken with a moſt violent pain in my head, and with not much leſſe in my ſtomack, That I
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:65062:58"/> feared it could not end but with a ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if not the Sickneſſe: and the more becauſe that Medicine of your which at other times was ever pleaſant to my taſte; was now ſo loathſome that I could hardly bring my ſelfe to take it: but confidering my neceſſity I forced down two ounces, which hardly ſtayed with me, nor did I hold it full halfe an hour; for then after much ſtrugling in me it gave me a large vomit, immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after which not finding my ſelfe ſo well as I hoped, though much relieved, I called fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my Glaſſe, and took two ounces more: ſoon after which I fell to reſt, ſleeping quietly all the night, and waked in the morning as if I had not been ill at all, and ſo remained ever ſince for which I bleſſe God and freely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelfe your debtor.</p>
               <p>Then for their prevalence in Cure, Being in the Country where I wrought and furniſhed my ſelfe with requiſites for any occaſion: and frequently ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65062:59"/> thoſe I left in <hi>London,</hi> with what was much wanted: not thinking of any Practice, but only for our own Family: By a Letter from a Stranger ſeaven miles off, I was thus treated, Sir by my good Friend Mr.—I underſtand you have a Soverain Water for the Plague: He told me a Gentlewoman gave him part of a Glaſſe, whoſe Husband refuſed to take of it and died: but ſhe and her two Maids took it and lived, wherefore I would deſire you to ſend me a pint of it, for I fear my Servant dyed of it on Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day laſt: I knew by the money he ſent what he intended, which I ſent with a taſte of another, his Wife and another Servant fell ill immediatly both having Riſings: he ſent for more, and often and had alſo of other ſorts, for he ſpared for no coſt: and the iſſue was, that his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant after a while recovered without breaking: but his wifes grew very large and was long in ripening, but at length it brake very kindly, and ſhe ſuddenly
<pb facs="tcp:65062:59"/> thereupon perfectly recovered: he told his friend alſo he believed, he himſelf was three times infected, but then taking larger quantities than ordinary; he ſoon ſenſibly perceived the venom to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, and deemed himſelf happy in hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them.</p>
               <p>Then for quick diſpatch in other dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous caſe, where in the Mineraliſts will ſtill preſume preheminence, openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing that without Antimony &amp; Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver, the Armory of Phyſick would be left deſpicably poor and indigent: whilſt to me they ſeem more the Parents of Diſeaſes than of Cures; and thoſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and long laſting even from gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to generation in Families: but whereas there are preparations of theſe critical ingredients ſaid to be as ſafe as the moſt innocent Cordials: for aſſurance the preſcribers will not ſcruple the trial of this <hi>Touchſtone.</hi> But for quick deſpatch in cure, beſides what the former Inſtances afford, I think indeed more than ſufficient,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:65062:60"/> cured as ſpeedily and with far more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and ſecurity: yet for an over-plus, take therewith theſe as an over-plus.</p>
               <p>One of which is, Of a young Man in my Country neighbor hood, weekly for halfe a yeer, after a dangerous ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: in dead of Winter fell into a violent looſneſſe, which infeebled him exceedingly and at three weeks end, ran into the bloody Flux with extreme griping, thirſt, and utter l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe of appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, working day and night and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him of all reſt: about ten in the morning my help was deſired by his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo I ordered him ſix ounces of an appropriate Medicine to be taken a little warm in four equal parts at each an hours diſtance: and at five in the afternoon to let me know how he was, during all which time he had no motion to ſtool, nor any deſire to drink: yet then I order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him two ounces of another to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken laſt that night; with which and no other, he became ſo well that next day
<pb facs="tcp:65062:60"/> he went abroad about his occaſions, troubled neither with gripes, looſneſs nor thirſt, nor want of appetite, but ſo hungry that he refuſed nothing.</p>
               <p>Another is of a Lad about thirteen, who from a fierce Ague, fell into ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Fever, that he became frantick, riſing in the night in a mighty in flamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and crying out fire, fire, that the houſe was on fire, and ſought a place to get out at: I ordered him four ounces of of an appropriate Medicine, the one half to be inſtantly given and the other four hours after, except there were manifeſt ſigns of amendment: and if ſo to reſerve it for next night; the firſt ſettled him, and next night he had the reſt: after which they gave me no accompt, but reckoned him well; becauſe he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and complained not: but hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he reſted not well, nor came to his ſtomach as thoſe uſe who recover up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Medicines I wondered I was not ſent to; but at laſt his mother perceiving
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:65062:61"/> he was not like to grow it out, ſhe came and I gave her two ounces of another of the Medicines ſutable to his preſent ſtate; with which he recovered.</p>
               <p>Two Children alſo, paſt all hope, recovered by each four ounces of an appropriate Medicine, given by little and little.</p>
               <p>And another of whoſe life the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents deſpaired: by four ounces of theſe Medicines recovered alſo.</p>
               <p>A young youth taken with a violent Ague and Feaver, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, recovered by ſix ounces of one of the Medicines.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman about fourty, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what out of order, was perſwaded by his friend to take ſuch a remedy, as he uſed to take himſelf, which putting his body into a ſtrange confuſion, with purging and vomiting, forced him to require other aid from Phyſitians, who although they ſomewhat allayed the diſtemper; yet he remained extreamly
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65062:61"/> depreſſed and ſinking in his Spirits, which continued upon him with fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and irreſiſtable ſighings; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon applying himſelf to the uſe of theſe reviving Medicines, in few dayes time, was enabled with cheerfulneſs to walk abroad, and purſue his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires.</p>
               <p>A Child not full a year and half old, through large and cold eating, falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a Surfet and Feaver, with thirſt, vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, looſneſs, gripings and cough; the Parents upon good knowledge, depending ſolely upon theſe Medicines, with variety and good quantity, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recovered the Child, when it was thought impoſſible, and without any inconvenience following, though ſhe took at leaſt two quarts of them, in no very long time.</p>
               <p>A Gentlewoman, who from a health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Conſtitution, and good Appetite; through Cold and Surfet, falling into a Feaver, with continual Head-ach,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65062:62"/> Reſtleſneſs, loſs of Appetite, obſtinate Obſtructions, with extream Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly, and ever upon ſinking for want of breath: by conſtant uſe of divers of theſe Medicines for a ſeaſon, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recovered.</p>
               <p>A young Gentlewoman big of her firſt Child, afflicted with ſo violent, and ſo perpetual a Cough, that it was thought impoſſible but ſhe muſt miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; taking every time ſhe cought of one of the Medicines appropriate to the Infirmity, to the quantity of a pint in one night, beſides what ſhe took the day before, quit her ſelf clearly of her diſtemper, without any the leaſt evil enſuing.</p>
               <p>A young Gentlewoman, upon the leaſt taking cold, or error in dyet, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into extream pains and feavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhneſs that put her in ſtrong Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſivemotions; upon taking for two or three dayes and nights ſome plenty of divers of theſe Medicines,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:65062:62"/> hath ever moſt wonderfully reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman, through much ſitting and writing, falling into a weakneſs of the brain and lightneſs, that he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually inclin'd to fall as he went about the ſtreets: by conſtant uſe of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate Medicine, carried alwaies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, and ſipping of it in ſmall quantity: perfectly recovered, as divers others have likewiſe done by the ſame means.</p>
               <p>One in her lying in, extreamly troubled with after pains; by taking onely two ounces of a general Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, found inſtant and great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman ſubject to a Cough, upon an extream cold and overſtraining, his body; his Cough not onely increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but a moſt violent pain in his ſide enſued, which ſo tormented him every time he cought, that tore him as it were in peices, yet in ſome four dayes,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:65062:63"/> uſing plenty of theſe Medicines, he was reſtored to his uſual Cond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>A young Lad languiſhing under ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream weakneſs, and waſted almoſt to nothing, by a pint of one of theſe Medicines proper in Conſumptions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered perfectly.</p>
               <p>A Gentlewoman ſwoln moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly with a Dropſie, uſing much counſel and means for reliefe, found none like what ſhe had by the uſe of one of theſe Medicines, appropriate to this diſtemper; and when ſhe was ſo hugely big, that the Phyſitians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, there was no way but by drawing the water which ſo ſwelled her, out with their uſual Manual ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſhe refuſing and caſting her ſelf wholy upon God, in the uſe of this Medicine after a ſhort time, the water ariſe and drain'd it ſelf out of her mouth dayly in large quantity, till ſhe recovered her ordinary health and due proportion.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:65062:63"/>
               <p>A Gentleman who had quite loſt his appetite, by the uſe of one of theſe Medicines, laſt at night, and firſt in the morning, perfectly recovered.</p>
               <p>His wife lying In, and in a violent reſtleſs Feaver, by a pint of another of theſe Medicines perfectly recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>And his next neighbours, being all down with ſickneſs, and one of them dying, fearing it to be the ſickneſs, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted them with theſe Medicines; and with the uſe of two pints they all recovered.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman about the age of forty, but newly recovered of a Pluretick di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, upon an extream Cold fell into a violent Feaver, which after ſome means and time ended in an Ague, which tormented him for divers fits both cold and hot, every other day three or four fits, were trifled away with ſlight Medicines, which unadviſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities thruſt him upon; at length,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65062:64"/> I undertaking him, in his firſt cold fit gave him in three hours time, a full pint of ſo high and powerful a Medicine; as would have amazed any Phyſitian, which yet without any prejudice, by burning or binding, or over-ſweating him, broke the heart of his Ague, and ſo by plying him on his well dayes and nights, ſometimes with the ſame in ſmaller quantity, and with others of like nature, at the fourth fit it was quite diſcharged; wherein were full experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of their reſtraining violent ſweats and thirſt, and in giving of reſt: all which are the peculiar effects of their benign temperature, which nor only renders my compound Medicines, but thoſe of meere ſimples, whether of Mint, Cinamon, Clove and the like, ſo far different from thoſe of the ſame mildneſs and pleaſantneſs, wanting the humane true temperature, that both in health and ſickneſs, the one ſhall do real ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, where the other doth miſchief in one kind or other.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:65062:64"/>
               <p>Theſe, though not neere the whole of what might have bin collected, of cures of this kind—much leſs of thoſe, who have cured themſelves by a draught or two in their firſt illneſs, and ſo eſcaped fits of ſickneſs, and courſes of Phyſick; nor of ſuch who have dayly ſupplyed their ſpirits, and fortified their natures, by their uſe in dyet and refreſhment, unto which they are eſſentially proper; yet I conceive are abundant proofs of their real virtue and effecacy: and that thoſe marks and characters ariſing from them, are not irrationally propoſed, as a teſt or Touchſtone of real Medicine; and for diſtinction of ſuch as may be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly truſted in cure; from thoſe which are not, and that with out, any outward violence, by Bleedings Iſſues, Cliſters, Bliſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or any inward diſturbance to the body, by Looſning, Vomiting, or other enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by Minerals, may ſuffice in all
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:65062:65"/> caſes and extreamities, to the comfort of all the ingenious, both perſons and families; who taking this for their guide, need not hence forth be ſo much to ſeek for reliefe as formerly, in times of ſickneſs and neceſſity. Every of thoſe Medicines pointed at, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be had,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>At the <hi>Star</hi> in the <hi>Poſtern</hi> by little <hi>Moorefields, London,</hi> 
                     <date>1667.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
